芜湖~
Okay, cool.
欢迎来到“缺失的学期”第三堂课。
So, welcome to the third lecture of the missing semester of your CS education.
今天我们要讲述的是文本编辑器。
Today we're going to be talking about text editors.
我非常喜欢这个话题。
This is a topic that I really like.
我认为这是我们在这门课程中教授的最有价值的话题之一，
I think it's one of the most valuable topics that we're teaching in this class ,
因为作为程序员，
because as programmers,
你们花费了大量的时间来编辑文本和程序，
you spend so much of your time editing text and editing programs that
如果你们投入时间使自己更高效地编辑，
if you invest time into making yourself more efficient at doing this,
你们将会节省大量的时间，
you'll save a ton of time,
也许在你们的本科阶段或职业生涯中，能够节省数百个小时。
probably hundreds of hours over the course of your undergrad or over the course of your career.
文本编辑器与其他编辑程序有所不同，
So text editors are a little bit different than other programs you might use to edit, say,
例如用于编辑英语散文的程序，因为编程与撰写英语散文不同。
things like English prose because programming is different than writing English prose.
在编程时，
When you're programming,
你需要花费大量的时间阅读你所编写的内容，
you spend a lot of time reading what you've written,
花费大量的时间在缓冲区中导航，
you spend a lot of time navigating around a buffer,
并花费大量的时间进行小的编辑，
and you spend a lot of time making little edits to code all over the place,
而不是像写文章时那样连续写作。
rather than just writing in a long stream like you do when you're writing an essay or something.
因此，用于这些不同目的的程序也不同，对吧？
And so it makes sense that there are different programs for these different purposes, right?
比如说，用于写文章的 Microsoft Word
So yeah, things like Microsoft Word for writing essays
和用于写代码的 Vim、Emacs、VS Code 和 Sublime 等等。
and things like vim and Emacs and VS Code and Sublime for writing code.
学习文本编辑器并成为熟练使用者的方法是从教程开始学习。
So, the way you learn a text editor and become really good at it is you start with a tutorial,
这基本上就是今天讲座的内容，
and so that's basically going to be the function of today's lecture,
再加上我们为你们提供的练习。
plus the exercises we've given you.
然后，在教程之后，你需要使用编辑器来完成所有的编辑任务。
And then after the tutorial, you need to stick with the editor for all your editing tasks.
当你学习一个复杂的工具时，
And when you're learning a sophisticated tool,
比如今天我们要教你 Vim，
so today we're going to teach you vim,
这是很多程序员使用的一个强大的编辑器，
which is one powerful editor that a lot of programmers use,
当你刚刚开始学习这个强大的工具的时候,
when you're learning such a sophisticated tool,
可能会让你的编辑速度有所下降.
it may be the case that initially
switching to this tool slows you down a little bit when you're programming,
但请坚持下去，因为我保证，大约使用新的编辑器编程20个小时后，
but stick with it because I'd say that in about 20 hours of programming using a new editor,
你会重新达到使用旧工具编程的速度。
you'll be back to the same speed at which you programmed using your old tool,
之后，你会开始受益，
and then after that, the benefits will start,
随着你的不断学习，你会变得越来越快。
and you'll get faster and faster as you learn more.
对于像 Vim 这样复杂的程序，
With these sophisticated programs like vim,
学习基础并不需要太长时间，但需要一辈子去掌握。
it takes not way too long to learn the basics but a lifetime to master.
因此，在你使用这个工具的整个过程中，
And so throughout the time you're using this tool,
请确保你随时查询相关资料来帮助你进行编辑。
make sure you look things up as you go.
如果你遇到这样的情况，
If you ever get to a point where you're like,
“哦，这种做事情的方式真的很低效，有更好的方式吗？”
"Oh, this is a really inefficient way of doing things. Is there a better way?"
答案几乎总是肯定的，
The answer is almost always yes
因为这些文本编辑器是由程序员为程序员编写的，
because these text editors were written by programmers for programmers
所以当然，
and so of course,
像编写这些工具的人一样，他们遇到了相同的问题并解决了它们，
like the people who wrote these tools, ran into the same kinds of issues and fixed them
这样你就不必再去处理这些问题了。
so that you don't need to deal with these anymore.
因此，在你学习的过程中，确保你查阅资料时要注意及时搜索，
And so yeah, as you're learning, make sure you look things up as you go,
可以使用谷歌或者随时给我们发邮件，如果有问题可以来参加办公时间，
either use Google or feel free to send us emails if you have questions or come to office hours,
我们会帮助你快速地解决问题。
and we'll help you figure out how to do things really fast.
至于要学习哪种编辑器，
As far as which editor to learn,
在之前的几个版本中，我们实际上避免教授特定的编辑器，
in previous iterations of this class, we actually avoided teaching a specific editor
因为我们不想把我们的观点强加给大家，
because we didn't want to enforce our opinions on you guys,
但我们认为教你如何使用一种特定的工具并善加利用它非常有用。
but we actually think that it's really useful to teach you
how to use one particular tool and use it well.
因此，人们对编辑器有着非常强烈的观点，
And so people have really strong opinions about editors,
所以你可以在课程笔记中查看更多关于这个主题的链接。
so you can see the course notes for more links on this topic.
回顾这些年来哪些编辑器比较受欢迎，
Looking at which editors have been popular over the years,
我相信你们都听说过 Stack Overflow，
Stack Overflow, I'm sure you've all heard of that,
他们每年都会进行一次调查，询问开发人员各种问题，
does a survey every year asking developers various questions,
其中一个问题是你使用哪种文本编辑器，
and one thing to ask is which text editor do you use,
目前最受欢迎的图形编辑器似乎是 VS Code，
and it seems to be that currently, the most popular kind of graphical editor is VS Code,
而基于命令行接口的最受欢迎的编辑器是 Vim。
and the most popular editor that is based within a command line interface is vim.
因此，我们将会教授你 Vim，
So we're going to be teaching you vim,
这样做有几个原因。
and there are a couple of reasons for this.
其一是我们所有的讲师，
One is that all the instructors,
包括我、Jon和Jose，都将 Vim 作为我们的主要编辑器使用，
so me, Jon, and Jose, use vim as our primary editor,
我们使用它已经很多年了，
and we've been doing this for many years,
也非常满意。
and we've been very happy with it.
我们认为它背后有很多有趣的思想，
We think that there are a lot of interesting ideas behind vim,
因此即使你最终不会使用这个特定的工具，
so even if you don't end up using this particular tool in the long term,
学习这些思想也是有价值的。
I think it's valuable to learn these ideas.
此外，许多工具都非常兴奋地关注 Vim 中的思想，
Also, a lot of tools have actually been really excited about the ideas in vim,
并支持 Vim 模拟模式。
and so they support a vim emulation mode.
例如，今天最流行的编辑器 VS Code 支持 Vim 绑定。
For example, VS Code, what is apparently the most popular editor in use today, supports vim bindings,
截止目前，这个Vim仿真模式已经有大约1.4百万次下载。
and this vim emulation mode as of now has like 1.4 million downloads.
在本次讲座的过程中，
As you'll see over the course of this lecture,
你会发现很多不同的工具都可以支持Vim仿真模式，包括你的shell、Python REPL和Jupiter notebook等等，
a lot of different tools, including your shell, including things like the Python,REPL and Jupyter notebook,
甚至你的网络浏览器也可以支持Vim仿真模式。
and all sorts of other things, even your web browser, can support a vim emulation mode.
所以，我们今天将教授你这个非常棒的工具，
So yeah, we're going to be teaching you this really neat tool today.
并且在这个讲座中，我们无法涵盖所有内容，因为它是一个非常强大的工具，
And in this lecture, we can't really cover all of them, right, it's a very powerful tool,
但是我们的目标是教授你核心的哲学，即其背后的真正棒的想法，
but our goal is to teach you the core philosophy of them, like the really neat ideas behind it,
以及一些基础内容，
and then in addition to that,
比如如何打开文件、关闭文件、在文件中导航、进行编辑，
some of the basics like how do you open a file, close a file, navigate around a file, make edits,
或者别的什么。
and things like that.
你可能无法记住本次讲座中的每一个小细节，因为我们会快速地浏览一些材料，
You may not remember every single little detail from this lecture because we're gonna go pretty fast through some of the material,
但是所有内容都在讲义中，
but it's all on the lecture notes,
而且练习还会为你提供一些教程和链接。
and then the exercises actually give you links to some tutorials and things.
因此，我强烈建议你至少完成所有非高级练习。
So I highly recommend that you actually go through all the exercises, at least the non-advanced exercises.
目前有问题吗？太好了。
Any questions so far?
好的，
Great.
Vim的一个非常酷的想法是它是一个模态编辑器。
Okay so one of the really cool ideas behind vim is that vim is a modal editor.
这是什么意思？"模态"源于"mode"这个词，
What does this mean? Modal comes from the word mode,
这意味着Vim有多个操作模式。
and this means that vim has multiple operating modes,
这种想法的发展源于编程时
and this is kind of developed from the idea that when you're programming,
经常需要做不同类型的事情，
there are often times where you're doing different types of things.
例如有时你在阅读代码，
Like sometimes you're reading code,
有时你在对代码进行小修改，
sometimes you're making small edits to code,
例如找到某个位置并更改某个小细节，
like you're finding a particular point and changing a little thing somewhere.
有时你只是一口气写很多代码，例如从头开始写一个函数。
Sometimes you're just writing a lot of code in one go, like suppose you're just writing a function from scratch.
因此，有不同的操作模式来处理这些不同类型的任务。
And so there are different operating modes for doing these different types of things.
因此，我实际上会在黑板上写下这个内容，这样我将来可以很方便地参考。
And so I'm actually going to write this down on the blackboard so I'll have a useful thing to refer to later.
当你启动Vim时，它会启动到所谓的正常模式。
When you start vim up, it starts up in what's called normal mode.
在这种模式下，所有不同的键组合都会以一种方式进行操作。
And in this mode, all the different key combinations behave in one way.
然后有不同的键组合可以将您从正常模式切换到其他模式，
And then there are different key combinations that switch you between normal mode and other modes,
这些模式会更改不同键的含义。
which change the meaning of different keys.
因此，在大多数情况下，您将会在正常模式或所谓的插入模式下花费大部分时间。
So for the most part, you'll be spending most of your time in vim in normal mode or what is called insert mode.
要进入插入模式，您需要按下“i”键，
And to go to insert mode, you press the key "i" for normal mode,
要从插入模式返回正常模式，您需要按下“Escape”键。
and to go from insert mode back to normal mode, you press the "Escape" key.
这里是关于符号的一些说明，因为我们以后会用到。
A little note on notation because we'll need this later.
在我在本课程中使用的符号
In the notation, I'm going to be using in this lecture
以及Vim用于给您反馈的符号中，
and what's also in the lecture notes and what vim uses to give you feedback,
有几种不同的方式来谈论不同的键。
they have a couple of different ways of talking about different keys.
因此，当他们谈论裸键时，比如键盘上的“i”键，他们会说'i'。
So when they're talking about bare keys like just the "i" key on your keyboard, they'll just say "i" .
但是对于不同的键组合，比如当您按下“Ctrl”和某个键时，
But for different key combinations, like when you press "Ctrl" and something
比如说，"Ctrl-V"，它是大约三种表示方法中的一个。
like say, Ctrl-V, it's notated in one of approximately three ways.
其中一种表示方式是插入符号("^")，然后是控制字符“v”。
One way that can be notated is a caret and then the control character "v".
所以这就是"^v"。
So this is "^v".
另一种可能会写成
Another way this might be written I think,
我认为我们在课堂笔记中是这样写的，是"Ctrl-v；
we've written it this way in lecture notes as "Ctrl-v",
这可能是您更常见的方式。
this is probably the one you're more used to seeing.
在其中的一些部分，这是以""的形式写出的。
And then in some parts of vim, this is written as "".
所以这是一些以后有用的符号表示。
So just a little bit of notation that will be useful later.
所以，Vim有几种不同的模式，
So yeah, vim has a couple of different modes,
其中正常模式是用于
where normal mode is designed for
在文件中导航，阅读内容，从文件到文件等。
navigating around a file, reading things, going from file to file, things like that.
然后插入模式是您键入文本的地方。
And then insert mode is where you type in text.
因此，在此处按下的大多数键将进入文本缓冲区，
So most keys that you press here will just go into your text buffer,
而在正常模式下按下的键不会放入缓冲区，
whereas keys that you press here are not being put into the buffer
而是用于导航或进行编辑。
and instead are used for things like navigation or making edits.
实际上，情况要复杂得多。
And actually, the picture is a little bit more complicated than this.
还有许多其他模式，
There are a whole bunch of other modes,
我将在此处写下它们，因为以后我们会参考它们。
and I'm just gonna write them down here because we'll have them here to refer to later.
因此，Vim还有一种替换模式，
And so vim also has a replace mode,
用于覆盖文本，而不是插入文本并将其推到前面。
for rather than inserting text and kind of pushing what's ahead of it forward, it will overwrite text.
然后，它具有许多不同的选择模式，
And then it has a bunch of different modes for selection,
因此它具有称为可视模式的模式，
so it has a mode called visual mode,
还具有可视行和可视块。
and then it has visual line and visual block.
这一个通过按下 r键输入；这一个通过按下 v键输入；这一个通过按下 Shift-b 输入，
This one is entered via the "r" key; this was entered via the "v" key; this one is entered via "s-v",
这一个则是通过按下 Ctrl-v 输入。
and this one is entered via "".
然后，还有一个命令行模式，可以通过冒号键（“：”）进入。
And then there's the command line mode, which is entered via the ":" key.
好的，既然我们已经将它们写在板子上以便以后参考，现在我们可以试着实践一下了。
Okay, so now that we have that on the board to refer to later, we can actually try some of this out.
我们注意到的一件事是，
All right, so one thing we noticed looking at that picture
从正常模式转到任何其他模式，我们需要按下某个键，
is that to go from normal mode to any of the other modes, we press some key,
但是从其他任何模式回到正常模式时，
but to go from any of the other modes back to normal mode,
我们会浪费大量的时间，
where we spend a lot of our time,
因为我们使用键盘上的 Escape 键。
we use the "Escape" on our keyboard.
因此，由于在使用 Vim 时你会频繁按下 Escape 键，。
So for this reason, since you'll be pressing the "Escape" a lot when using vim,
很多程序员会重新绑定键盘上的某个键为 Escape 键，
a lot of programmers rebind one of the keys on their keyboard to be Escape,
因为用左手小指去按键盘角落的那个小 Escape 键非常不方便
because it's really inconvenient to reach up with your left pinkie to press that tiny little "Escape" in the corner of your keyboard.
因此，许多人使用大写锁定键（“CapsLK”），
And so a lot of people use the "CapsLK" key instead,
因为它就在主键盘区，
so it's right there in the home row,
我们在讲义中提供了如何进行按键重绑定的链接。
and we have some links in the lecture notes for how you can do this key rebinding.
好的，既然我们已经讨论了 vim 的核心思想之一，
Okay, so now that we've talked about kind of one of the core ideas of vim,
即模态编辑的思想，我们可以讨论一些基础知识，
the idea of modal editing, we can talk about some of the basics,
比如如何打开这个文本编辑器，如何打开和保存文件等。
like how do you open up this text editor, how do you open file save files, and things like that.
因此，这是一个基于命令行的程序，虽然也有一些图形化的变体，
And so this is a command-line based program, although there are some graphical variants,
但是你启动这个程序的方式是运行 Vim。
and the way you start this program is by running "vim".
你可能会注意到，在我屏幕的左下角，他们实际上看到了我刚才输入的内容。
One thing you might notice is that in the bottom left corner of my screen, they actually saw what I just typed.
在这节课上这将十分有用，当我输入 Vim 命令时，
This will be useful later in this lecture, where I'm actually typing in commands for vim,
我会说出我输入的内容，
and I'll be saying what I'm typing,
但你也会在屏幕上看到它。
but you'll also see it on the screen.
所以，如果我按下Ctrl+c键，你会看到那边显示^c。
So if I press "Ctrl+c", you'll see it says "^c" over there.
这段字大家都能看清楚吗？
Is that text big enough for everybody to read?
太好了，那么我们打开Vim的方法就是在命令行中运行vim程序，
Great. okay, So the way we open Vim is just by running the program "Vim" on our command line,
大多数系统都预装了它。
and this comes pre-installed on most systems.
如果你没有它，你可以使用你的包管理器进行安装。
If you don't have it, you can install it using your package manager.
如果我们想要用它来编辑特定的文件，Vim也可以接受一个参数，
vim can also take an argument if we want to use it to edit a particular file
而不仅仅是打开程序
instead of just opening up the program then later opening a file.
例如，我有一个文件在这个目录中；这实际上是这个讲座的讲义。
So for example, I have a file in this directory; this is actually the lecture notes for this lecture.
所以，我可以输入"vim editors.md"，按"ENTER"，
So, I can do "vim editors.md" and press "ENTER",
然后瞬间就开始了。
and then boom, vim is started.
在这个讲座中，我将不会在完整的Exton中运行Vim。
And then in this lecture, I'm not running vim in the completely Exton configuration.
我配置了一些默认行为比较好的东西，
I've configured a couple of things that behave a little bit nicer by default,
比如在左边有行号，或者在底部有更多的状态信息等等。
little things like having line numbers on the left or having some more status information on the bottom.
如果你想使用这个默认配置开始，
If you want to start with this default configuration,
我们在讲义中有一个链接，你可以自动得到一个稍微更加合理的配置。
we have a link to this in the lecture notes so you can get a slightly more sane config by default.
那么，一旦你打开了Vim，你要怎么做呢？
So, once you've opened vim, what do you do?
嗯，就像我之前说的那样，Vim开始在normal模式下。
Well, as I said earlier, vim starts in normal mode.
所以，如果我开始打字，比如输入“X”，它不会将“X”插入到缓冲区中。
So, if I just start typing letters like, say, type "x", it doesn't insert "x" into the buffer.
你可以看到左上角的光标：它实际上删除了一个字符。
You can see the cursor up in the top left: it actually deleted one of the characters.
那是因为我在normal模式下，而不是insert模式。
That's because I'm in normal mode, not insert mode.
所以，insert模式基本上是你过去使用过的所有其他文本编辑器所熟悉的，
So, insert mode is basically what you're used to with all the other text editors you've used in the past,
其中有一个光标，当你打出一个字符，
where there's a cursor somewhere, you press the character,
它就会进入到你的缓冲区。
and it just goes into your buffer.
在Vim中，你开始是在normal模式下，
I'm instead in vim, you start in normal mode,
你可以按“i”键进入insert模式。
and you can press "i" to go into insert mode.
所以，我按下了“i”，然后注意到底部左侧的提示说“INSERT--”。
so see I've pressed "i", and then in the bottom left, notice that it says "INSERT--".
底部左侧总是告诉你你现在处于哪个模式下，除了normal模式，此时是空白的。
The bottom left always tells you what mode you're in, unless this normal mode, in which case it's blank.
现在，我处于insert模式下，如果我按下“x”键，它就会被插入到我的文本缓冲区中，
Now that I'm in insert mode, if I press the "x" character, for example, it just gets inserted into my text buffer,
我可以退格删除它，输入其他内容，
and I can backspace over it, type other stuff,
现在我的文本编辑器就像你预期的任何其他程序一样运行。
and now my text editor kind of behaves like you'd expect any other program to behave.
从这个点开始，如果我想停止插入字符，我该如何回到正常模式呢？
So from this point, how do I go back to normal mode if I want to stop inserting characters?
是的，确切地说，我按“Escape”键。这就是我的按键可视化功能的一个实例，
Yes, exactly. I press "Escape". And that's the symbol my keystroke visualizer uses for "Escape",
所以请注意这一点。
so just be aware of that.
Vim 认为使用鼠标效率低下。
Vim has this idea that using the mouse is inefficient.
就像你的手从键盘上移动到鼠标上需要很多时间一样，
Like, your hands are on the keyboard, moving your hand over to the mouse takes a lot of time, right?
你不想在编程时浪费那几毫秒的时间，对吧？
You don't want to waste those couple of milliseconds while you're programming, like in the middle of things.
因此，所有 Vim 功能都可以通过键盘操作。
So, instead, all vim functionality can be accessed just through the keyboard.
它可以像打开文件、保存文件等你可能习惯的方式进行操作，
And it's all sorts of things you might be used to doing, like opening files by going, like, "file open", or "file save",
也可以通过键盘访问。
or things like that, or instead accessed through the keyboard.
如何实现呢？
How is that done?
通过另一个 Vim 模式，
That's done through one of the other vim modes that are on the board over there.
即命令行模式来实现。
In particular, through command line mode.
因此，如果你处于正常模式，并按下“：”键，
So, if you're in normal mode and you press the ":" key,
你将看到光标……
you'll notice that the cursor……
我猜我的可视化功能刚刚显示过了，只不过它现在已经自动消失了
I guess my visualizer is covering the thing right now but it's gone.
你会注意到光标跳转到左下角，并显示我刚才输入的“：”符号。
The cursor jumps to the bottom left and it shows that ":" I just typed.
现在，我可以输入命令。
And now, I can type in a command.
你可以将其想象为我们过去几天谈论过的命令 shell，
So, you can think of this almost like the command shell that we've talked been talking about over the last few days,
只不过这是 Vim 的命令 shell，
except this is vim's command shell,
所以你在这里应该输入Vim命令，而不是 shell 命令。
so you give vim commands here, instead of shell commands.
有很多内置命令可以完成你所需的所有任务，
And there are a bunch of built-in commands that do all the things that you're used to.
例如你可能想了解的一个命令是如何退出编辑器。
Like, for example, one command that you might want to know is how to quit this editor.
如果你处于正常模式，
You might notice that if you're in normal mode,
我可以按“Escape”键从命令行模式返回到正常模式，
I can press "Escape" to go back from command line mode to normal mode,
而且与许多程序不同的是，我按“Ctrl-c”并不能退出 Vim。
and I press "Ctrl-c", unlike what happens to a lot of programs, this doesn't quit vim.
那么我该如何退出 Vim 呢？我可以按“：”，
So, how do I quit vim? I can press ":",
然后进入命令行模式，
and then go into command line mode,
我可以输入命令“quit”。
and then I can type in the command "quit".
“Q-U-I-T”。
"Q-U-I-T".
你会看到我 ……
You'll see that
也许我应该把这个移到中间或者其他地方
I maybe I should move this over to the middle or something.
看吧，它显示“:quit”，然后我按下 ENTER键，就退出 Vim 了。
See, it says ":quit" and I press "ENTER",and it quits vim.
我可以再次打开 Vim。
I can open vim up again.
其实这个命令有一个缩写形式，只需要输入“:q”，
There's actually a short form for this command, just ":q",
就可以达到同样的效果。
and that'll do the same thing.
还有很多类似这样有用的命令。
And, there are a bunch of other useful commands like this.
所以，还有一些其他方便的命令需要知道，比如如何保存文件？
So, some other handy ones to know are how do you save a file?
假设我在这里进行了一些编辑，比如“hello world”。
So, suppose I make some edits here, like "hello world".
所以，我按下“i”进入插入模式
So, I pressed "i" to go into insert mode
或者让我重做一遍
or let me redo that.
我按下“i”进入插入模式。
I press "i" to go into insert mode.
现在，我可以使用向下箭头...
Right now, I can use "the down arrow" to...
我觉得我稍微需要修改一下。Jon，你可以修复一下配置吗？
I think I've slightly I should fix that. Can you fix the config, actually, Jon?
不要在意。
Never mind that.
好的，
Okay,
假设我跳到这一行，
so, suppose I go down to this line,
然后按下“i”进入插入模式，
and I press "i" to go into insert mode,
输入一些文本，
and type in some text,
然后按下“Escape”回到正常模式。
and then press "Escape" to go back to normal mode.
那么，我该如何保存这个文件呢？嗯，这里有另一个命令。
Now, how do I actually save this file? Well, there's another command for that.
所以，输入“：”进入命令模式，
So, ":" to go into command mode,
然后我可以输入“w”,
and then I can type "w"
然后按“Enter”。
and press "Enter".
“w”代表写入。
"w" stands for write.
底部显示“editors.md”等等，
And, it says in the bottom "editors.md" whatever blah blah written.
意思是文件已经保存，所以现在，如果我输入“：q”退出。
And so, this means it saved the file and so now if I ":q" to quit
然后重新打开同一个文件，你会看到更改已经被保存了
and open the same file, again, you'll see that the changes have been persisted.
还有一些其他命令...
There are a couple other there's...
所以，有很多不同的 Vim 命令，因为不同的原因非常有用。
So, there's a ton of different vim commands that are useful for different reasons.
但是我现在会再向你解释几个命令。
But, I'll just explain a couple more to you now.
一个非常有用的命令是“help”，准确的说是“:help”。
One command that's really useful is "help", ":help".
你可以通过输入“：help”，
And you can do ":help",
再输入一个特别的按键或是命令
and then type in a particular key, or a particular command,
你就可以得到对应的帮助文档。
and get help for that keystroke or that command.
所以，如果我想知道“:w”命令的作用，我可以使用“:help :w”，
So, if I want to know what ":w" does, I can do ":help :w",
这会给我带来“:w”或“:write”的文档。
and that'll give me the documentation on ":w" or ":write".
如果我执行“:q”，它会关闭这个窗口并把我带回到之前的位置。
If I do ":q", it'll close this window and bring me back to where I was before.
请注意，“:help :w”和“:help w”是不同的，
And, notice that ":help :w" is different from ":help w",
因为w键是正常模式下按下w键，
because the "w" key is the w that, like, when you're in normal mode and press "w",
这里是不需要加“：”的。
what happens is just the "w" key here without the ":".
如果我查找“：w”的帮助，那就是“:w”命令的帮助。
And, if I look for help for ":w", that's the help for the "w" command.
现在，你已经掌握了基本的操作方法，对吧？
So, now you basically have the bare fundamentals needed to use vim, right?
你可以打开编辑器，
You can open the editor,
编辑一个特定的文件，
use it to edit a particular file,
按“i”键进入插入模式并输入一些文本，
press "i" to go into insert mode and type in some text,
按“Esc”键回到正常模式，
press "Escape" to go back to normal mode,
然后“：w”保存更改，“：q”退出。
and then ":w:" to save your changes, ":q" to quit.
所以，你已经掌握了使用Vim编辑文件的基本技能，尽管有些效率低下。
So, like already you have the bare fundamentals necessary to edit files using vim, that will be somewhat inefficiently.
到目前为止有问题吗？是的，在后面。
So, any questions so far?  Yeah in the back.
问题是，正常模式有什么好处？
Yeah so the question is, What's the benefit of the normal mode?
我们将在五分钟内更详细地讨论这个问题。
And, we'll talk about that in more detail, in like five minutes.
但简单来说，插入模式只用于输入文本。
But, in short, insert mode is just for typing in text.
所以，在插入模式，我可以输入文本。
So, I'm in insert mode, I can type in text.
但是实际上，当我编程时，我花了很多时间移动我的文件并进行小的修改。
But, when I'm programming, I actually spend a lot of time moving around my file making small little changes.
所以我来到这里，想把这个“https”链接改成“http”链接。
So, I go here and like, oh maybe I want to change this "https" link to an "http".
我可以在正常模式下进行小的编辑和修改，
I can make like small point edits, things like that, in normal mode.
我们将在五分钟内看到更多这样的内容。
And we'll see a whole lot more of that in about five minutes.
好问题！还有其他问题吗？
Good question! Any other questions? Okay cool.
好的，继续讲，
So, moving along,
我认为还有一件事情有点有用，
one other thing that's kind of useful to know, I think,
在高层次上，Vim的缓冲区模型与窗口模型和选项卡模型。
is, at a high level, vim's model of buffers versus windows versus tabs.
那么，你之前使用的编辑器，比如Sublime Text或VS Code，
So, it's probably the case that whatever program you were using before, like Sublime Text or VS Code or whatever,
你肯定可以在它们中打开多个文件，
you could open multiple files in it, right,
并可能有多个标签页和多个窗口。
and you could probably have multiple tabs open and have multiple windows open of your editor.
Vim也有这些不同的概念，
So, vim also has a notion of those different things.
但它的模式与大多数其他程序有些不同。
But, its model is a little bit different than most other programs.
Vim维护了一组打开的缓冲区——这是它用于打开文件的术语，它有一组打开的文件。
So, vim maintains a set of open buffers--that's the word it uses for open files.And so, it has a set of open files,
然后，与此分开，您可以有多个标签页，
and then kind of separately from that, you can have a number of tabs,
每个标签页可以有窗口。
and tabs can have windows.
这使得Vim与您之前使用的程序略有不同，
The kind of weird thing which makes vim a little bit different than the program you've probably used in the past is that
因为缓冲区和窗口之间不一定是一对一的对应关系。
there isn't necessarily a one-to-one correspondence between buffers and windows.
例如，我可以在这里做一件事,
So, one thing I can do, for example, here
稍后我们将向您展示组合键和其他内容
and we'll show you the key combinations and stuff for this later
你可以创建两个不同的窗口。
but one thing you can do is create two different windows.
这样一来，我在上面有一个窗口，
So, I have one window up here,
在下面也有一个窗口。
and then one window down here.
请注意，同样的文件在两个窗口中都打开。
And, notice that the same files open in both windows.
因此，如果我在这里进行一些编辑，它们实际上也会在下面的窗口中发生，
So, if I make some edits over here, they actually happen in the bottom window, as well,
因为两个窗口中打开的是同一个缓冲区。
because it's the same buffer that's open in both windows.
这对于同时查看文件的两个不同部分非常有用。
And, this is kind of useful, for, say, looking at two different parts of a single file at the same time.
所以你想能够在文件的顶部查看程序的导入，
Like, so you want to be able to look at the top of a file,
同时在下面的其他地方工作。
say at an import to your program, while you're down below, working somewhere else.
所以这是一个有用的东西需要记住，Vim有这种想法——有几个标签页，
So, this is one helpful thing to keep in mind, that vim has this idea of - there are a number of tabs,
每个标签页有一些窗口，
and each tab has some number of windows,
然后每个窗口对应一个缓冲区。
and then each window has, uh, corresponds to some buffer.
但是，一个特定的缓冲区可以在零个或多个窗口中同时打开。
But, a particular buffer can be open in zero or more windows at a time.
这是我最初学习Vim时困惑的一件事，
Just one thing that confused me when I was initially learning vim,
所以我想早些解释一下。
so I want to explain that early on.
然后，我们之前提到的“：q”命令不完全是退出。
And then, the ":q" command, which we talked about earlier, is not exactly quit.
它有点像关闭当前窗口，
It's kind of close the current window,
然后当没有更多的打开窗口时，Vim才会退出。
and then, when there are no more open windows, vim will quit.
所以，如果我在这里输入“:q”，它只会关闭上面的窗口，因为那是我所在的窗口，
So, here, if I do ":q", it'll only close the window, I think, on the top here because that's the one I was in,
现在剩下的窗口变成了全屏模式。
and, now, the remaining window becomes fullscreen.
我可以再次输入“:q”来关闭这个窗口。
I can do ":q" again to close this.
现在我们在我打开的第二个选项卡中。
Now we're in the second tab that I'd opened.
如果我再次输入“:q”，好的，现在Vim退出了。
If I do ":q" final time, okay, now, vim exits.
如果你不想一遍一遍地按“:q”，
And if you don't want to press ":q""" way too many times...
好，现在我这里有是三个窗口
Okay, so, here I have three split windows.
你可以输入“:qa”来关闭所有打开的窗口。
If I do ":qa", for quit all, it closes all the open windows.
好的，回答你的“正常模式究竟是用来干什么的”问题。
All right, so, now, to answer your question of "What is normal mode actually for?"
这是Vim中另一个非常酷的想法，
This is another, really cool idea in vim,
我认为这实际上是这个程序最基本和有趣的想法。
and I think this is actually, like, the most fundamentally interesting idea of this program.
就是像你们都是程序员一样，
It's that, like, you're all programmers,
你们都喜欢编程
you like programming;
Vim有这样一种想法，就是Vim的正常模式，
vim has this idea that vim's normal mode,
Vim的界面本身就是一种编程语言。
like, vim's interface, itself, is a programming language.
让我重复一下，
And, let me repeat that.
这是一种非常有趣的想法：界面就是一种编程语言。
That's like a kind of fundamentally interesting idea - the interface is a programming language.
这是什么意思？这意味着不同的按键组合有不同的效果，
What does that mean? It means that different key combinations have different effects,
一旦你学会了不同的效果，你就可以将它们结合在一起
and, once you learn the different effects, you can actually combine them together
就像在编程语言中一样，
Just like in a programming language，
你可以学习不同的函数或者其他的，然后将它们粘合在一起，制作一个有趣的程序。
you can learn different functions and stuff and then glue them all together to make an interesting program.
同样，一旦你学会了Vim的不同的移动和编辑命令等等，
In the same way, once you learn vim's different movement and editing commands,
你就可以通过编程Vim来与Vim交流。
and things like that, you can talk to vim by programming vim through its interface.
一旦这变成了肌肉记忆，你就可以以你思考的速度编辑文件。
And, once this becomes muscle memory, you can basically edit files at the speed at which you think.
对于我来说，我不认为我能够用过去使用的任何其他文本编辑器做到这一点，
Like at least for me, I don't think I've been able to do this with any other text editor that I've used in the past,
但这个编辑器非常接近。
but this one gets pretty close.
那么，让我们深入了解正常模式的工作原理。
So, let's dig into how exactly normal mode works.
你可以尝试跟着这个进行操作，打开Vim中的一些随机文件，
So, you can try to follow along with this, like, open up some random file in vim,
并跟随我输入的一些键组合。
and follow some of the key combinations I type in.
所以，一个基本的事情是你可能想做的，就是在文本中浏览，
So, one basic thing that you might want to do, is just navigate around a buffer.
移动你的光标上下左右。
Like, move your cursor up/down/ left/right.
在 Vim 中，你可以使用 hjkl 键来实现，而不是箭头键。
And so the way you do that in vim, is using the "hjkl" keys, not the arrow keys.
虽然默认情况下箭头键也可以工作，但尽量避免使用它们，
Though they do work by default, try to avoid them,
因为你不想一直将手移动到箭头键，
because you don't want to have to move your hand all the way over to the arrow keys.
这浪费了很多时间。
like there's a ton of time you're wasting, right?
而 hjkl 键在键盘的主键区上，
"hjkl" is right on the home row.
j键向下移动，k键向上移动，h键向左移动，l键向右移动。
And, so, "j" moves down, "k" moves up, "h" moves left, and "l" moves right.
这可能现在看起来有点不直观，
And, this may seem a little unintuitive now,
这里有很多历史原因
there was some historical reason for it,
例如早期vi设计师使用的键盘有“hjkl”键，
like the keyboard the original vi developer used had the "hjkl" keys,
例如通过标记和排布使得更加合理
like labeled and arranged in a way that made this more reasonable.
但是很快就会成为肌肉记忆。
But, this will very soon become muscle memory.
这是在普通模式下移动光标的基本方法。
So, this is the basic way you can move your cursor around while in normal mode.
现在，还能做什么呢？
Now, what else can you do?
如果我们像这样移动文件，速度会非常慢。
Well, if we had to move around files like this, it'd be really slow.
我们不想按住这些键，
We don't want to have to hold down these keys,
然后等待 Vim 完成它的操作。
and like, wait for a long time for vim to do its thing.
所以，还有其他不同的按键组合可以进行不同的移动。
And so, there are all these other, different key combinations for doing different movements.
顺便说一下，这些都在讲义中，
Also, by the way, this is all in the lecture notes,
所以你不需要现在就记住每个键及其含义。
so you don't need to memorize every single key and its meaning right now.
只要试着理解 Vim 的界面是一种编程语言的总体思想。
Just try to understand the overall idea that vim's interface is a programming language.
还有一件事情可以做，就是按下 w键。
So, another thing you can do is press the "w" key.
这将使光标向前移动一个单词。
This moves the cursor forward by one word.
类似地，b键向后移动一个单词。
And then, similarly, the "b" key moves the cursor backward by one word.
因此，在同一行内进行更有效的移动。
So, this allows slightly more efficient movement within the line.
还有 e键可以将光标移动到单词末尾。
There's also the "e" key for moving to the end of a word.
我将它移动到一边。
I'm going to move this over a little bit.
例如，如果我在这里，
So, if I'm here, for example,
按“E”键，它会跳到这个单词的末尾，下一个单词的末尾，依次类推。
and I press the "e" key it'll go to the end of this word, end of this word, end of the next word and so on.
你也可以整行移动，
You can also move by whole lines,
所以“0”移动到行的开头，“$”移动到行的末尾，
so "0" moves to the beginning of a line, "$" moves to the end of a line,
“^”移动到行的第一个非空字符。
and "^" moves to the first non-empty character on a line.
让我举个例子。
So, let me find one of those, for example.
在这里，我的光标就在这里；
So, here, my cursor's right here;
如果我按“0”，我的光标就会移到行的开头，“$”是当前行的末尾；
if I press "0", my cursor goes to the beginning of the line, "$", end of the current line;
如果我按“^”，光标会停留在哪个字符上呢？
and if I press "^", where, like, on what character will the curser end up?
有人能猜到吗？
Can anybody guess?
按“^”会移到行的第一个非空字符上，有点像正则表达式中的“^”。
So, "^" goes to the first non-empty character on a line, kind of like Regex "^".
没错！它会移到这个连字符（“-”）上。
Yeah, exactly! It goes to this "-".
我们再谈谈一些移动命令。
Let's talk about some more movement commands.
有一些方法可以在缓冲区中上下滚动，
There're ways to scroll up and down in a buffer,
所以“Ctrl-u”向上滚动，
so "Ctrl-u" goes up,
“Ctrl-d”向下滚动。
and "Ctrl-d" scrolls down.
这比按住k或j键要好得多。
So, this is better than holding down the "k" or "j" keys, for example.
当然这比整页移动要慢得多。
This is a lot slower than moving by entire pages.
“Ctrl-d”和"Ctrl-u"。
"Ctrl-d" and "Ctrl-u".
还有一些方法可以整个缓冲区移动。
There's also ways to move by the entire buffer.
所以，大写的“G”会移动到底部...
So, "G" moves all the way down...
“gg”会移动到顶部。
"gg" moves all the way up.
其中一些移动键是助记符；
Some of these movement keys are mnemonics;
因此，它们更容易记住，
so, they're like, a little bit easier to remember for that reason right,
例如，“w”是单词，“b”是单词开头，“e”是单词结尾。
like, "w" is word, "b" is beginning of word, "e" is end of word.
它们都很合理。
Those all seem pretty logical.
“0”，“^”和“$”符号，有点受到正则表达式的启发，
"0", "^" and "$", kind of inspired from Regex,
因此它们有点合理。
so those make a little bit of sense.
还有一些其他的按键，可能没有太多意义，
There's some other ones that, like, don't necessarily make way too much sense,
但是键盘上的键只有那么多，
but, there are only so many keys on your keyboard,
你能怎么办呢？
so what are you going to do?
例如，按下 "l" 键将光标移动到屏幕上显示的最低行。
For example, the "l" key moves your cursor to the lowest line that's shown on the screen.
"l" 表示最低，"m" 表示中间，
"l" for lowest makes sense, "m" for middle,
"h" 表示最高，我想这很有道理。
and then "H" for highest, I guess.
还有很多其他有趣的移动方式，
And, there's a whole bunch of other interesting movements like this.
我们显然无法在此处全部介绍，
So, we're obviously not going to be able to cover all of them right now,
但你可以通过 Vim 教程练习进行学习，这是本课程的第一个练习。
but you'll be able to go through them in the vim tutor exercise, which is exercise number one for this lecture.
现在我想再谈谈其他一些移动方式，也许我只谈论其中一种。
Some other ones I want to talk about now - maybe I'll talk about one more.
还有一种叫做 "查找" 的移动方式。
There's another movement called "find".
这也很有用。
This is also kind of useful.
假设我在这一行上，
Suppose I'm on this line,
我想跳转到第一个等于...
and I want to jump to the first character that equal to...
比如我想跳到第一个 "o"。
Like, I want to jump to the first "o".
我可以按下 "fo"，
I can press "fo",
光标就会移动到第一个 "o"。
and my cursor moves to the first "o".
我就会找到 "o"。
I've like, found "o".
我可以按下 "fw" 就会跳到第一个 "w"，我想是在这里。
I can do "fw" and it'll move to the first "w", which I think is right here.
我可以按下 "fc"来查找第一个 "c"。
"fc" find the first "c".
我也可以做相同的事情，但是向后移动。
I can also do the same thing, but backwards.
如果我按下大写的 "F"，然后再按下 "w"，我就可以找到它前面的 "w"。
If I do "Fw", I can find the "w" that's before it.
大写的 "F" 和 "s"：找到前面的 "s"。
"Fs" find the "s" that's before that.
然后，还有一种查找的变种——“t”（表示“to”），
And then, there's a variant of "f" for "find" - "t" for "to",
所以我可以跳转到“o”，
so I can jump to "o",
直到找到 o 为止。
and it jumps, like, until it's found "o".
但不是在它的顶部，而是在它之前一个字符的位置。
But not on top of it, right before it.
而大写字母 T，比如说 “T”，向后跳到字符 “T”，但不是跳到它的顶部，而是跳到它的前一个字符。
And "T" say, "T" jumps backwards to the t except not all the way on top of it, one character before.
所以，你已经可以看到
And so, you can already see
我谈到Vim 是一种编程语言的想法，你可以组合这些命令。
that idea I talked about of like, vim is a programming language; you can, like, compose these commands.
“f”和“t”是“查找”和“到”的意思，你可以查找特定的字符，或者跳转到特定的字符。
"f" and "t" are "find" and "to", and you can say find a particular character, or jump to a particular character.
这些是几个 Vim 的移动命令。
So, those are a couple of vim movement commands.
那么，对于这些命令有没有问题？有问题吗？
So, any questions about those so far? So this is... yeah, question?
好的，很棒。
No? Okay, cool.
这些是 Vim 的移动命令，
So, those are vim movement commands.
它们可以帮助你在正常模式下快速地在文件中导航。
This is how you can navigate around a file quickly in normal mode.
现在，另一类有用的命令是编辑命令。
Now, another category of useful commands are editing commands.
我们已经谈到的一个是“i”命令，用于从“正常”模式切换到“插入”模式，
So, one we kind of already talked about is the "i" command for moving from normal mode to insert mode,
在那里你可以开始编写文本。
where you can start just writing text.
所以，假设我跳到这里并按下“i”键，
So, suppose I go up here and I press "i".
现在我可以输入任何文本，比如“Hello World”，然后按下“Enter”键。
Now I can type in whatever text I want "Hello world", "Enter".
然后，按下“Escape”键回到正常模式，
Then, press "Escape" to go back to normal mode,
我就对我的缓冲区进行了修改。
and I've made a change to my buffer.
但是，在处理编程语言时，
But, there are a whole bunch of other commands for making efficient edits
还有很多其他命令可以进行高效的编辑。
that makes sense for when you're dealing with programming languages.
一个有用的命令是我之前无意中使用过的“o”命令。
So, one useful command that I accidentally used earlier, before teaching you about it, is the "o" command.
假设我的光标在这里，
So, suppose my cursor is, like, over here,
如果我从正常模式按下“o”，它会在光标下方打开一个新行。
and if I press "o", from normal mode, what it does, is it opens a new line below where my cursor is.
这就是“o”的含义。
That's what "o" stands for.
它会创建一个新行
And it, so it creates a new line,
并进入插入模式，
and it put me into insert mode.
这样我就可以开始输入一些文本，
So, now I can start typing in some text, press "Escape",
按下Esc键回到正常模式.
and go back to normal mode.
就像“o”命令一样，还有一个大写的“O”命令，
And then, just like the "o" command, there's a capital "O" command,
所以如果我在这里，按下大写的“O”，它会将我放到当前位置的上方的插入模式中。
so if I'm here and I do capital "O", it puts me into insert mode above where I currently am.
还有另一个Vim命令可以删除东西。
There's another vim command for deleting things.
假设我的光标在这个单词上方，
So, suppose my cursor is, like, on top of this word right here,
我按下d键。
and I press the "d" key.
“d”代表删除。
"d" for delete.
噢，没有反应.好吧，原来d键需要与移动命令结合使用。
Oh, nothing happens; turns out that the d key needs to be combined with a movement command.
所以，记得我们刚刚讨论过不同的移动命令，比如hjkl
So, remember we just talked about different movement commands, like "hjkl",
、word、backward word等等。
and, like, word, and backward word, and things like that.
所以我按下d键。
So, I press "d".
我按下d键，然后按下w键，
I press "d" and I can press "w",
它就删除了一个单词。
and it's deleted a word.
让我撤销一下。
So, let me undo that.
在Vim中撤销只需要按u键。
Undoing in vim is just "u" for undo.
注意我的光标在这里。
So, notice my cursor's right here.
我按下“dw”,它删除了一个单词。
I do "dw", it's deleted a word.
我可以移动光标，
I can move around,
然后再删除另一个单词。
and then delete another word.
假设我在……
Suppose I'm... uh, keeps getting in the way. Suppose I'm, like,
在单词的中间，
somewhere in the middle of a word,
想要删除到单词末尾。
and I want to delete to the end of a word.
你猜我需要使用哪个键的组合呢？是 "d" 和什么？是 "de"，没错。
Any guesses for what combination of keys I'd use for that? "d" and what? "de", exactly.
删除到单词末尾。
Delete to the end of the word.
另一个有用的编辑命令是 "c" 命令，
Another useful editing command is the "c" command.
c 代表 "change"（改变）。
"c" stands for change.
所以，改变和删除非常相似，
So, change is really similar to delete,
但改变会将你置于插入模式，因为我想删除一个东西，
except change puts you in insert mode, because, like, I want to delete a thing,
但要将它改变为其他东西。
but change it to something else.
因此，如果我在这里，
So, if I'm here,
输入 "ce"，就像是将其改变到单词的末尾。
and I do "ce", it's like, change to the end of the word.
它会删除内容直到单词的末尾，
And, it gets rid of the contents until the end of the word,
并注意到它将我置于插入模式。
and notice it put me in insert mode.
现在，我输入的任何字符都会进入缓冲区。
So now, whatever characters I type go into the buffer.
如果我按下 "Escape"，我就会回到正常模式。
If I press "Escape", I go back into normal mode.
因此，c 和 d 是相似的：它们都需要一个移动作为参数。
And so, "c" and "d" are analogs: they both take motions as arguments.
它们将删除或更改该运动。
And, they will either delete that motion, or change that motion.
例如，如果你按下 "c" 键，
So, for example, if you press the "c" key,
也有这种模式，如果你连续按两次特定的编辑键,
there's also this pattern that, if you press a particular editing key twice,
它会在给定的行上产生相应的效果。
it'll have that effect on the given line.
所以，如果我按下 "dd"，那就会删除该行。
So, if I press "dd", that deletes the line.
如果我按下 "cc"，那就会删除给定的行，
If I press "cc", that deletes the given line,
但将我置于插入模式，这样我就可以用其他行替换它。
but puts me in insert mode, so I can replace it with some other line.
我们将涵盖一些其他的编辑命令，
We'll cover a couple other, uh, editing commands,
因为稍后我们将看到所有这些命令如何相互作用。
because then later we'll see how all these things interact together.
因此，另一个有用的命令是 "x" 命令。
So, another useful one is the "x" command.
假设我的光标在某个特定的字符上。
So, suppose my cursor is over some particular character.
如果我按下"x"，它只会删除该字符。
If I press "x", it just deletes that character.
还有另一种命令叫做"r"。
There's another command called "r".
如果我在某个特定的字符上，
If I'm over a particular character,
按下"r"，它会将另一个字符作为参数，
and I press "r", it takes another character as an argument,
并用另一个字符替换该特定字符。
and it replaces that particular character with some other character.
我将介绍另外几个编辑命令。
And, I'll cover a couple more editing commands.
其中一个我在前几分钟已经提过了
So, I think one I talked about a moment ago
当然，你可以撤销在Vim中所做的更改。
but, of course you can undo changes you've made in vim.
而且你在普通模式下按下"u"就可以了。
And the way you do that is by pressing "u" while you're in normal mode.
所以，"u"代表撤销很容易记住。
So, "u" for undo is pretty easy to remember.
我按下了"u"多次；它撤销了我所做的所有更改。
So, I press "u" a whole bunch of times, it's undone all the changes I've made.
然后，撤销的相反是重做。
And then, the opposite of undo is, of course, redo.
在Vim中，重做的绑定键是“Ctrl-r”。
And, the binding for that in vim is "Ctrl-r".
好的，我将讲一下复制和粘贴，因为...哦，是的，有问题吗？
All right, one other editing command I'm going to talk about is copy and paste because... Oh yes, question?
那是一个很好的问题！
That's a great question!
问题是，“'undo'是撤销自进入插入模式以来所做的所有更改，还是只撤销最后一个字符？”
So, the question is, "Does 'undo' undo everything you've done since you've gone into insert mode, or just the last character?"
实际上比这还要复杂一些。
It's  actually a little bit more complicated than that.
"撤销"会撤销你所做的最后一次更改。
"Undo" does, like, undoes the last change you've made.
所以，如果你进入插入模式，
So, if you went into insert mode,
输入了一些东西，
and typed in some stuff,
然后回到正常模式，
and went back into normal mode,
然后按下"u"进行"undo"，它会撤销你在插入模式中所做的所有更改。
and then press "u" for "undo", it'll undo all you've done in insert mode.
但是，如果你做了其他类型的编辑命令，比如说我按下"x"删除一个字符...
But, if you've done some other type of editing command, like, say I press "x" to delete a character...
如果我按"u"进行撤销，它只会撤销那个编辑命令所做的更改。
If I do "u" for undo, it'll just undo that change that that editing command made.
现在，这回答了你的问题吗？(是的)很好，还有其他问题吗？好的。
Now, does that answer the question? Great! Any other questions? Cool!
我也会讲一下复制和粘贴，因为那是一个受欢迎的命令。
So, I'll talk about copy and paste as well, because that's a popular one.
y命令表示复制，
The "y" command stands for copying,
而p命令则表示粘贴。
and the "p" command stands for pasting.
y代表"copy"，是因为“yank”
"y" for copy, because, "yank".
“yank”是Vim用于复制的术语。
Like, that's the word they... That's the terminology that vim uses for copying.
这些命令也可以接受一个动作作为参数。
And, these commands are "y" also takes a motion as an argument.
例如，如果我键入yy，它将复制当前行。
So if I do like, "yy", it copies the current line.
如果我按下“p”进行“粘贴”，
And, if I press "p" for paste,
请注意现在这两行是相同的，因为我刚刚粘贴了一行。
notice that now these two lines are identical, because I've just pasted a line below.
"u"表示“撤销”。
"u" for undo.
但是如果我做类似“yw”的操作，它会复制单词。
But if I do something like "yw", it's copied the word.
然后我可以按下“p”，
And then I can do "p",
它会在光标所在位置再次粘贴该单词。
and it just pasted that word again, right where my cursor was.
在复制和粘贴的上下文中，特别有用的一件事是能够选择一块文本并将其复制。
One useful thing, especially in the context of copy and paste,is to be able to select a block of stuff and copy it, right?
这可能是您在以前使用的任何编辑器中使用复制和粘贴的方式。
Like, this is probably how you used copy and paste in whatever editor you were using before.
因此，这就涉及到了视觉模式。
And so, that's where we get into the visual modes.
这些是一组彼此相关的模式，
So, these are another set of modes that are all related to each other,
可以从普通模式进入，
and that can be reached from normal mode,
用于选择文本块。
and they're used for selecting chunks of text.
其中一个模式是普通视觉模式。
So, one mode is, just, regular visual mode.
您可以通过按v进入该模式。
You can enter that by pressing "v".
进入此模式后，您可以使用大多数常规的普通模式命令来移动光标。
And then, once you're in this mode,you can use most of the regular normal mode commands to move your pointer around.
它会选择两点之间的所有文本。
And it selects everything in between.
因此，我可以使用hjkl来移动光标，或使用“w”按单词移动，或使用不同的命令
So I can use, like, "hjkl" just to move the cursor, or I can use "w" to move by words, or different things like that,
来选择文本块。
and it will select a block of text.
一旦我选择了这个文本块，就有许多不同类型的有用的操作可以进行。
And, once I've selected this block of text   there are a whole bunch of different types of useful things you could do with it.
最常见的操作之一是将其复制。
One of the most popular things to do is copying this.
所以，一旦我选择了文本块，我可以按y复制，
So, once I've selected, I can do "y" to copy,
然后回到正常模式。
and it puts me back into normal mode.
现在，它已经将所选文本块复制到粘贴缓冲区中。
And now, it's copied this to the paste buffer.
然后，如果我去其他地方，
And then if I go somewhere else,
按下“p”，它会将我刚刚复制的整个文本块粘贴在那里。
and press "p", it pastes in that whole chunk of text I copied.
这类似于视觉模式，可以选择连续的文本流。
And it's similar to visual mode, which selects kind of a contiguous stream of text.
有个视觉行模式，可以通过按大写V可到达该模式，
There's visual line mode so that can be reached by pressing "V",
并且一次选择整行。
and that selects whole lines at a time.
然后还有视觉块模式，可以通过按“Ctrl-v”
And then there's visual block mode, which can be selected by pressing "Ctrl-v",
来选择矩形块文本。
and that can select rectangular blocks of text.
因此，这是您以前的编辑器无法完成的操作。
So this is something your old editor couldn't do.
好的，
Alright,
还有很多其他的 Vim 编辑命令需要学习。
so, there's a lot more vim editing commands to learn.
有许多非常奇怪和花哨的事情。
There's lots of, like, really weird and fancy things.
例如，波浪线命令（“~”）可以更改字符或当前所选内容的大小写。
Like, for example, the "~" command changes the case of the character,or the selection that you've currently selected.
因此，例如，我可以选择 Visual Studio Code
So for example, I can take this, like, "Visual Studio Code",
并翻转整个内容的大小写，然后按“~”。
and flip the case on the whole thing, by selecting it and pressing "~".
还有许多类似的东西，它们随着你的学习会变得越来越深奥。
And, there's a whole bunch of other things like that, they get more and more esoteric as you go.
因此，我们不会涵盖所有这些内容，
So, we're not going to cover all of those,
但您将在练习中了解到它们。
but you'll get to those in the exercises.
这些是 Vim 编辑命令，
So, those are vim editing commands,
其中许多可以与移动命令组合使用。
and a lot of them can be composed with movement commands.
对于以上内容是否有疑问呢？很棒。
So, any questions about either of those so far? Cool.
接下来，与正常模式相关的另一个命令类别是数量。
So, moving along, another category of things of commands that are mostly relevant to normal mode are counts.
您可以给它们一个数字，
So, you can give them a number, to do a particular thing,
以执行某个特定操作一定数量的次数。
some number of times.
假设我的光标在这里，
So suppose my cursor is here,
我想要向下移动1 2 3 4行。
and I want to move down, like 1, 2, 3, 4 lines.
一种方法是按下“j”键四次，向下移动四次，
One way I can do that is by pressing "j" four times, go down four times.
而“kkkk”则向上移动四次。
"kkkk" goes up four times.
但是，我可以使用计数来代替多次按同一个键。
But, rather than pressing a particular key again, and again, I can use a count.
所以，如果我按下“4”、“j”，它会执行四次“j”操作，对吧？Vim的界面就像是一个编程语言。
So if I press "4j", it does "j" four times, right? Vim's interface is a programming language.
如果我按下“4k”，它会向上移动四次。
If I do "4k", it moves up four times.
如果我在这里，
If I am here,
按下“v”进入可视模式...
and I press "v" to go into visual mode...
好的，现在我可以移动光标并选择文本块。
Okay so now I can move my cursor around, and select blocks of text.
我可以按“eee”选择几个单词，
I can do, like, "eee" to select a couple of words,
但我也可以回到这里。按“v”进入可视模式 - 并按三个“e”选择向前的三个“单词结尾”。
but, I could also go back here. "v" for visual mode and press "3e" to select, like, "three ends of words" forward.
当然，这些还可以与编辑命令相结合使用。
And then of course these can also be combined with editing commands.
比如，假设我想删除七个单词。
So, like, suppose I want to delete seven words.
我可以把光标移动到某个位置，
I can do that by moving my cursor somewhere,
然后输入“7dw”。
and doing "7dw".
删除七个单词。
Seven delete words.
这对于这样的情况特别有用：我的光标在屏幕上的某个位置，
And so, this is particularly useful for things like, suppose my cursor is somewhere on the screen,
我正在查看屏幕上的其他地方，或者我想让光标移动到那一行。
and I'm looking somewhere else on the screen, or, I want my cursor to go to that particular line.
请注意，我在左边设置了相对行号。
Notice that I've set up relative line numbering on the left.
因此，无论我的光标在哪里，它都显示当前行号，
So, wherever my cursor is, it shows the current line number,
但在其他地方，它只是相对于我的位置的偏移量。
but everywhere else, it's just the offset from where I am.
现在假设我的光标在这里，
Now, suppose my cursor is here,
但我想向下移动到像“Microsoft Word”这样的位置，
but I want to move down to the like "Microsoft Word" down here,
也就是往下8行。
so that's eight lines down.
那么，我应该按哪些键的组合来实现呢？也就是说，最有效的方法是什么？是的，就是这样！
So, what combination of keys would I press, to do that? Like, what's the most efficient way? Yeah, exactly!
我们试一试——按下8j，我的光标就移动到了这一行。
Let's try that out. "8j" and my cursor moved down to this line.
好的。最后，Vim中的一个关键意义类别是修改器。
Okay. And then, one final category of key meanings in vim is something called modifiers.
到目前为止，我们已经介绍了移动、编辑、计数，
So we have, so far, movement, edits, counts,
最后是修改器。
and, finally, we have modifiers.
修改器可以稍微改变移动命令的含义。
So, modifiers kind of change the meaning of a movement command a little bit.
其中两个特别有用的修改器是“a”和“i”。
And, a couple modifiers that are especially useful are the "a" and "i" modifier.
a代表around（周围），i代表inside（内部）。
So, "a" stands for like around and "i" stands for inside.
为了看到这个特别有用，我可以把光标移动到这里，例如。
And, to see where this is really useful, I can move my cursor to somewhere like here, for example.
希望你们中大多数人都熟悉markdown语法——如果不熟悉也没有关系。
So, hopefully, most of you are familiar with markdown syntax and if not it doesn't matter too much.
这是一个markdown链接；方括号（“[]”）中呈现出一段文本，括号中则是链接（“()”）。
Uh, this is a link in markdown, it's a text rendered in square brackets("[]"), and then the link in parentheses("()").
假设我的光标在这里，
Suppose my cursor is inside here,
我想更改与此链接相对应的文本。
and I want to change the text corresponding to this link.
嗯，我可以通过向后移动b，
Well, one way I could do that is, like, move back here with "b",
然后2dw，
and, like, "2dw",
再按“i”进入插入模式来进行更改。
and then "i" to go into insert mode.
这是我可以进行此更改的众多方法之一，
That's one of the many ways I can make this change,
我可以输入任何其他想要的内容——按u撤消，再按一次u。
and I can type in whatever other thing I want, "u" to undo, "u" to undo.
我还可以使用另一种方法，即更改两个单词——“c2w”，然后输入其他文本。
Another way I could have done that is change two words "c2w" and then type in some other text.
但是，我可以用修饰符命令来实现相同的更改，
But, one final way I could do the same change is using the modifier commands to talk about
以说明我想如何与括号和方括号这些不同类型的分组交互。
how I want to interact with these different types of grouping things like parentheses("()") and square brackets("[]").
因此，最后一种方法是更改方括号内部-“c”“i”“[”
So, one final way of doing this is change inside square brackets "ci["
这将使我进入插入模式，删除方括号内部的内容后。
and that puts me into insert mode, after deleting the contents that are inside the brackets.
你看到我们如何将所有这些不同的元素结合起来，例如我们谈到的“更改”，
So, do you see how we can take all these different ingredients, like we talked about "change",
我们可以将其与不同的移动命令组合在一起。
and we could combine that with different movement commands.
我们谈到了“inside”修饰符。
We talked about inside, how it's a modifier.
然后我们谈到了...
And then we talked about, uh...
我们没有谈到括号。
we didn't talk about parentheses("()").
但是，如果你的光标悬停在不同的分组元素，
But, if your cursor is hovering over a different, uh,
如括号或方括号上，
different types of grouping things like parentheses("()"), or square brackets("[]"),
你可以按百分号移动键在匹配的括号之间来回跳转。
you can press the percent movement key to jump back and forth between matching parentheses("()").
如果我走到这里并输入“di(”，我可以删除括号内的内容。
If I go over here and I do "di(". I can delete the contents inside these parentheses.
因此，这些是Vim的修饰符。
And so, those are vim, uh, modifiers.
我想我们谈到了“i”，
I guess we talked about "i",
但是我们没有谈到“a”。
but we didn't talk about "a".
如果我执行“da(”，它将删除一个完整的、包括括号的分组，
If I do "da(", it deletes a whole, like parenthesized group including the parentheses("()").
所以“i”表示内部，而“a”表示周围或包括。
So "i" is inside, "a"  is around or including .
这些基本上是您在与Vim界面交互时
All right so those are basically the different categories of things you can combine together,
可以组合在一起的不同类别的东西。
when interacting with vim's interface.
所以，有关这一点或这个界面作为编程语言的整体思路有任何问题吗？
So, any questions about that or the overall idea of this interface being a programming language?
很好。
Cool.
那么，让我们做一个快速演示，以展示此编辑器的强大功能。
So, let's do a quick demo, to kind of demonstrate the power of this editor.
它将帮助我们了解这个工具如何快速运作，并与我们思考的速度相匹配。
And, it will kind of help us see how this tool can work really fast and kind of match the speed at which we think.
这里有一个非常破损的“fizzbuzz”实现，实际上什么都没有打印。
So, over here is a very broken "fizzbuzz" implementation that doesn't actually print anything.
希望你们中的大多数人都听说过“fizzbuzz”，如果没有，我将简要解释一下。
Uh, hopefully, most of you have heard of "fizzbuzz" - if not, I'll explain it super briefly.
“fizzbuzz”是一项编程练习，在此练习中，您将打印从1到n的数字，
Uh, "fizzbuzz" is a programming exercise where you print the numbers 1 through n,
但当数字可以被3整除时，您将打印fizz-当它可以被5整除时，您将打印buzz。
but when the number is divisible by 3, you print fizz; when it's divisible by 5, you print buzz.
同时，当它能被3和5同时整除
And, when it's divisible by both 3 and 5,
它会打印fizzBuzz，
you print fizzbuzz.
如果不符合条件，就直接打印数字。
And, if none of those apply, you just print the number.
所以你应该打印1，2，Fizz，4，Buzz等等。
So, you should print like "1", "2", "fizz', "4", "buzz", and so on.
但是，如果我运行这个程序，它不会打印任何东西。
But, if I run this program, it doesn't print anything.
现在它们在左边，然后把它们放在右边的终端里。
Here, I have them on the left, in just a terminal on the right.
好的，所以这里有一堆问题。
Okay,so there's a bunch of issues with this.
其中一个问题是main从来没有被调用，
One is that main is never called,
所以让我们从修复它开始。
so let's start off with fixing that.
这就是我会如何进行更改的方式，请注意它只需要很少的按键：
So, here's how I would make this change and notice how few keystrokes this requires:
大写G表示跳到文件底部，o表示在下面打开一个新行，
capital "G" means go to the bottom of the file, "o" opens a new line below,
现在我可以输入一些东西了。
and now I can just type in stuff.
所以，我处于插入模式。
So, I'm in insert mode.
好的，我输入了我想要做出的任何更改，按Escape回到正常模式。
Okay, so I've typed in whatever change I want to make, "Escape" to go back to normal mode.
如果我输入:w（命令模式，右边），让我回到这里。
If I do ":w" (command mode, right), let me go back here.
好的，现在至少当我运行它时，我的程序会打印一些东西。
Okay, now at least my program prints something when I run it.
这个程序的另一个问题是它从0开始而不是从1开始，
Another issue with this program is that it starts at 0 instead of 1,
所以让我们去修复它。
so let's go fix that.
所以，我想去到这个范围
So, I want to go over to this "range" thing,
哎呀，这个范围的问题，它不应该从“0”到“限制”，而应该从“1”到“限制+1”。
and it shouldn't be going from 0 to "limit", it should be going from 1 to "limit+1".
我没有向你展示过的一个命令是如何在vim中搜索，
One command which I didn't show you about is how you search in vim,
所以按斜杠（/）关闭它并重新开始。
so you press forward slash ("/") to close this and restart it.
如果你按斜杠，它会开始搜索，
If you press forward slash("/"), it starts search,
所以如果我输入“范围”（enter），我的光标会从之前的任何位置跳转到它找到的第一个“范围”。
so if I type in "range" ,enter, my cursor goes from wherever it was before to the first instance of "range" it found.
所以，这是一种非常高效的移动方式。
So, it's a really efficient way of moving where I want to move.
“ww”可以向前移动两个单词，I可以进入插入模式，添加“1，”（逗号空格），然后退出，回到正常模式。
"ww" to move forward two words, I to go into insert mode,   add the "1", comma space, escape, I'm back in normal mode.
这是Vim中非常常见的模式：
This is a very common pattern in Vim:
保持在正常模式下，移动到某个地方，进入插入模式，进行微小的更改，
you stay in normal mode, you go somewhere, you go into insert mode, you make a tiny change,
然后立即返回正常模式，就像正常模式是主页一样，
and you jump right back to normal mode like normal mode is home,
大部分时间都应该在那里。
and that's where you should be most of the time.
我还想添加一个“+1”，所以按e键到这个单词的末尾，按a进入插入模式，然后输入“+1”，“Esc”。
I also want to add a "+1", so "e" to go to the end of this word, "a" for apend "+1", "Escape".
好了，问题解决了。
Alright, fix that problem.
这个程序的另一个问题是对于能被3和5整除的数都打印“fizz”，
Another issue is that this program prints "fizz" for both divisible by three and five,
所以让我们来解决这个问题。
so let's fix that.
输入“/fizz”搜索"fizz"，
"/fizz" searches for "fizz", been oppressed,
接下来查找下一个匹配项
and it goes to the next match.
“ci'”改变了‘ ’里面的内容
"ci'"  changes what's inside the quote(''),
接下来删除“fizz”，然后回到插入模式，更改引号内的内容，
so it's deleted the "fizz" and put me in insert mode right in between those two quotes(''),
最后按Esc回到正常模式。
and I can type in whatever I want, "Escape" to go back to normal mode.
很好，我解决了这个问题。
So, great, I've fixed that particular problem.
这个程序的另一个问题是，对于15的倍数，它在不同的行上打印“fizz”和“buzz”，
Another problem with this program is that it prints "fizz" and "buzz" on separate lines for multiples of 15,
所以我们要去解决这个问题。
so let's go and fix that.
让我到达这一行。
Let me go down to this line here.
我可以……
One way I can ...
实际上不用关心像程序的实际内容或是一些不重要的，愚蠢的程序内容
don't actually worry about like the actual contents of this program, like this some stupid program that doesn't matter
多关心我在vim中输入了什么，又是怎么高效地修改程序的
pay attention to what keys I'm pressing in vim that allow me to make changes to this program really efficiently.
我的光标在这一行上。
So, my cursor is on this line.
按“$”将光标移动到行尾，按i进入插入模式，
I press "$" to go to the end of this line, "i" for insert mode, okay,
然后输入一些内容，按Esc回到正常模式。
and I'm typing some stuff, "Escape" to go back to normal mode.
现在，我想进行与下面的打印相同的更改。
Now, I want to make the same change the print below.
看这里，
Look at this.
“jj.”
"jj.",
“.”这个命令在vim中表示重复执行前一个编辑命令，
So what "." does in vim is it repeats the previous editing command that was made,
这是一种不用一遍又一遍地输入相同内容来完成重复任务的好方法。
and so this is a really nice way of doing repetitive tasks without typing the same thing over and over again.
在这个例子中，它插入了“,”和“''”，并且当我按下“.”时，它在这一行上执行了同样的操作。
So in that particular case, that inserted comma and quote and so it applied the same thing on this line when I press ".".
接下来，我们将解决这个程序的另一个问题，
And then when I guess one final part of this demo is we will fix the issue that
即它可能应该使用命令行参数来代替这里硬编码的10。
this program maybe should take a command line argument instead of having this hard-coded 10 down here.
那么我们该怎么做呢？我按“gg”回到开头，然后按大写O，
So how do we do that? I'll press "gg" to go to the top, capital "O",
在上面打一行文字，如“imports this”，
so now I've opened a line above and I'm going to type in some text like "imports sys ",
按escape回到正常模式，
"Escape" to go back to normal mode,
然后我想到达这里的10，所以输入/10就跳到那里了。
And then I want to go down to where this 10 is. So "/10" makes me jump straight down there.
“ci(”用于编辑括号内的内容，
"ci(" to edit what's inside the parentheses("()")
现在我可以在这里输入任何我需要输入的内容,
and now I can type in like whatever thing I need to type in here
一旦完成，我的程序就能正确地执行fizzbuzz了。
and then once I've done this, my program does "fizz_buzz" correctly.
我想我漏了一个我想要的修改，但这没关系。
I think I missed one change I wanted to make, but it doesn't matter.
这证明了您可以快速地进行许多更改。
This demonstrates that you can make lots of changes really fast.
对于这个演示或我们一直在谈论的总体思路，有任何问题吗？
So any questions about this demo or the overall idea we've been talking about?
好的，这将在周二进行介绍，
Okay, so this will be covered Tuesday,
我在左边运行Vim的外部环境和右边的Shell，
so the kind of outside environment I'm running vim on the left and my Shell on the right,
这是外部的team ox。
and then this is tmux on the outside.
一个相关的问题可能是如何在不同的vim窗口之间切换，
One variant of that question might be like how do you switch between different Vim windows
您可以查看讲座笔记中的快捷键，
and you can see the lecture notes for that, but there's a key binding for that.
可以在同一个窗口或多个窗口之间进行切换。
So if you have the same window open or multiple things open, there's a way of doing that.
有问题吗？
Question?
啊，好问题。
ah, good question.
所以，delete命令接受一个运动命令，然后删除这些内容但保持在正常模式下，
So delete takes a motion and then removes those contents but keeps you in normal mode,
所以您可以继续执行其他操作。
so you can keep just moving around in a file.
而change命令非常类似于delete命令，
What change does is very similar to delete,
它也接受运动命令并以相同的方式处理它们，在文件中移动并删除这些内容。
it takes motions and treats them in the same way, deletes those contents,
但是它随后会进入插入模式，
but then puts you in insert mode,
从而节省了您打一个额外按键的时间。
and so it saves you from typing one extra keystroke.
例如，如果我在这里，我想删除“main”，可以用“dw”删除一个单词，
So if I'm here, for example, I want to delete "main", "dw" deletes a word,
但现在如果我按下J这样的按键，它会让我向下移动。
but now if I press whatever key likes I press "j", it just moved me down.
如果我撤消这个操作，再输入cw4更改一个单词，现在它实际上已经进入了插入模式，
If I undo that, do "cw" for change a word, now it's actually put me into insert mode,
我可以输入任何我想要插入的内容。
and I can type in whatever I want it to insert.
因此，“dwi”与“cw”相同，
So "dwi" is the same thing as "cw",
但后者节省了一个按键。
but it saves a keystroke.
我们在资源中提供了一个名为“vim golf”的东西。
One thing we've linked in the resources is something called "Vim golf".
基本上，人们在网上设置了一个游戏，
Basically, people have set up a game online
您可以得到一个编辑任务，并尝试找出完成编辑所需的最小按键数。
where you can get an editing task and try to figure out the minimal number of keystrokes necessary to complete that editing task.
它实际上非常容易上瘾。
It's actually really addictive.
所以我只建议在空闲时间进行游戏。
So I'd only suggest going on their chest and script time.
我想我看到有人举手提问了。
I think I saw a hand for another question.
对，句号。
Yeah, uh, period.
这是vim命令中最有用的之一。
Yeah, one of the most useful of vim commands.
好问题。
Good question.
还有其他问题吗？太棒了。
Any other questions? Cool.
所以我想我们还有大约五分钟的时间，
So I think we have about five minutes left,
我将简要介绍一个在笔记中也详细介绍的东西，
and I'm gonna briefly talk about a thing that's also covered in detail in the notes,
请务必查看这个笔记。
so make sure you look at the notes for this.
Vim是一款程序员的文本编辑器，
Vim is a programmer's text editor,
因此，它具有高度的可编程性。
and so of course, it's highly programmable.
不仅通过它的界面（它本身就是一种编程语言）而且还有其他几种方式。
Not only through its interface that's a programming language but also a couple of different ways.
有许多设置可以进行微调以匹配您的偏好，
There are lots of settings that you can tweak to match your preferences,
您还可以安装插件来完成各种有用的事情。
and you can also install plugins for them that do all sorts of useful stuff.
Vim 的配置方式是通过一个名为“vimrc”的磁盘文件来实现的，
So the way vim is configured is through a file on disk called "vimrc",
这在很多基于 shell 的工具中都是一种常见模式。
and you'll see this is a common pattern in a lot of shell-based tools.
这个纯文本文件配置了工具的运行方式。
There'll be a plain text file that configures how the tool works,
如果我编辑这个文件，它可能还没有在你的机器上存在，
and so if I edit this file and it may or may not exist on your machine yet,
但我们已经为你创建了一个默认的“vimrc”并在课程网站上提供了链接，
but I've downloaded the, we've created a kind of default "vimrc" for you and linked it on the course website,
你可以从那里开始。
so you can start with that one.
如果我输入 “vim ~/.vimrc”，
If I do "vim ~/.vimrc",
我可以看到一堆注释，然后是特定的命令，比如默认情况下，我们希望有语法高亮,
I can see here a bunch of comments and then particular commands like by default, we want syntax highlighting on,
同时我们需要行号
and we want line numbers.
如果我们没有进行一些配置，比如让我删除设置行号的那些内容，
If we didn't do some of these things like let me remove the stuff that sets line numbers,
如果我删除了这些配置并重新启动 vim，注意到左边就没有行号了。
if I remove those configurations and relaunch vim, notice that I no longer have line numbers on the left.
总之，你可以通过Vim配置很多东西，
But yeah, so in short, there's a lot of stuff you can configure with vim.
我们已经为你提供了一个非常基本的配置，
We've given you a very basic configuration
请尝试消除 Vim 中默认情况下的一些奇怪行为，
that tries to remove some of the kind of weird behavior that's on by default in vim,
但我们不会在你身上强加太多的其他观点。
but we don't really try to enforce too many of our other opinions on you.
当然，像我们三个人一样，都经常使用 Vim，我们已经完全习惯了vimrc。
But of course, like the three of us used vim a lot and we have heavily customized vimrcs.
所以如果你想借鉴一些东西，我们也链接了我们的个人配置，
So we've linked to our personal configurations too if you want to take anything from that,
此外，像数千万人一样，他们会在 Github 上分享他们的 vimrc，
and also, like thousands or millions of people share their vimrcs on Github,
所以有很多地方可以寻找灵感。
so there's lots of places to look for inspiration.
因为在这个平台有很多nice的博客
There are also cool blog posts on this topic.
在 Vim 中，你还可以使用插件来扩展它，这些插件可以做很多有用的事情。
Another thing you can do in vim is you can extend it with plugins that do all sorts of useful things.
这让你可以做一些模糊文件查找之类的事情，这是很多文本编辑器默认就有的，
This lets you do things like fuzzy file finding, which a lot of text editors come with by default,
所以你可以得到一个弹出窗口，
so you can get like a pop-up window,
输入一个文件名或大致的文件名，
you can type in a name of a file or approximately the name of a file
非常快速地找到它，或者有些插件可以显示撤销历史的可视化效果，
and find it very quickly, or there are things that show you like visualizations of undo history.
有些则可以显示文件浏览器，还有很多其它功能的。
There are things that show you like file explorers, things like that.
所以我们在课程网站上链接了一些我们最喜欢的插件，
So we've linked to a couple of our favorite plugins on the course website,
我强烈建议你熟悉如何安装插件，
and so I highly recommend becoming familiar with how to install a plugin
因为这只需要三秒钟，而且其中一些非常酷。
because it takes like three seconds and some of them are really cool.
在下课前，我将简要讲述一下一个话题
And then finally, the last topic I'll briefly mention before we finish today's lecture
Vim 模式和其他程序
is vim mode and other programs.
事实上，许多程序员都对 Vim 的界面感到兴奋，
So turns out that a lot of programmers were really excited about vim's interface,
因此他们在其他工具中实现了类似的功能。
and so they've implemented similar functionality in other tools.
例如，我已经将 Python REPL 配置为在 Vim 模式下运行。
For example, like I've configured my Python REPL to run in vim mode.
因此，我可以在这里键入内容，
So I can type in stuff here,
如果我按下 Escape 键，现在我就在 Python REPL 中的普通模式中了。
and if I press "Escape", now I'm in normal mode in my Python REPL,
我可以前后移动，按 x删除内容，使用“cw”更改一个单词
and I can move back and forth and like press "x" here to delete a thing, like "cw" to change a word
或是其它有意思的事。
and do all those good things.
不仅如此，
And it's not just the Python REPL.
我的终端也是这样工作的。
Like, I have my terminal behaving this way too.
我可以在这里键入任何内容，然后按 Escape 键，
So like, I can type in whatever I want here and "Escape",
就在普通模式中了。
and I'm in normal mode.
我可以进入终端内部的可视化模式，选择文本块，
I can go here and like go into visual mode inside my terminal and like select blocks of text,
按“~”键更改大小写，等等。
press tilder("~") to change the case, whatever.
因此，我们提供了如何为 bash、zsh、fish，
So we've linked to how exactly you can enable vim mode for like bash, zsh, fish,
以及很多基于 readline 的程序（如 Jupyter、Notebook）启用 Vim 模式的链接，还有许多其他工具。
a lot of readline-based programs like Jupyter Notebook, a whole bunch of other things.
如果没有提供链接，您可能可以通过搜索找到它，
And if it's not another place, you can probably find it by googling it
因为许多人喜欢这种功能。
because a lot of people like to have this sort of functionality.
如果您真的打算学习 Vim，
And if you're really gonna commit to learning vim,
我认为在使用的每个工具中启用这种 Vim 模拟模式是很有价值的。
I think it's valuable to enable this sort of vim emulation mode in every tool you use.
一是可以更好地学习工具，
It's like one, or like make you learn the tool a lot better,
二是一旦你变得擅长 Vim，这些技能将转移到你使用的所有其他工具上。
and two, once you become good at vim,like those skills will now transfer to all your other tools you use.
好的，这就是我们对 Vim 的快速介绍。
Okay, so I think that's it for our rapid introduction to vim.
我们无法在今天的讲座中涵盖所有有趣的内容，
There's some other neat material that we weren't able to fit in today's lecture,
但这些内容在讲义中都有涉及。
but it's in the lecture notes.
最后，我强烈建议您完成今天的练习。
And then finally, I highly recommend going through the exercises for today.
至少对我个人来说，
Like, at least for me personally,
我认为学习文本编辑器
I think spending time learning my text editor
是我们这门课教授的最有益的知识。
has been like the most beneficial thing out of the kinds of things we're teaching in this class.
好了，今天的讲座就到这里，
So yeah, that's it for today's lecture,
明天见。
and we'll see you tomorrow.
请注意，我们已将明天的讲座改为数据整理。
Note that we've changed tomorrow's lecture to data wrangling.
周二和周四的讲座现在已经互换了。
Thursday and Tuesday lectures are now switched.
如果有人只打算来听其中一个讲座，请查看课程网站。
This is reflected on the course website in case anybody was going to come to one but not the other.